Banks are taking more steps to distance
themselves from this growing private
credit mess. They have been
re-evaluating assets that have been
pledged to them to secure financing. I
told you a month ago when JP Morgan did
this, there would be others to follow,
and we just got confirmation there was.
But that's only the half of it.
Insurance companies, they continue to be
dragged further and further into this
growing mess, which is understandable
given their exposures to it. Got some
big news as far as insurance companies
go, a double dose of stage two.
Now, what JP Morgan had done in March
was reduce the value of private credit
assets that could be pledged to the bank
as collateral for obtaining basically
emergency loans, but also some other
kinds, too. The point of doing that was
to effectively limit access to JP
Morgan. In other words, JPM was
distancing itself from the mess by
making it harder for shadow banks to
borrow from it. But now we've got
confirmation the rest of the banking
sector is furiously trying to protect
itself, too. And we'll go over what that
means, and what it is they're exactly
doing. It's not good, nor is the other
big story, insurance companies. The
annuity underwriters and retirement plan
product managers, it was only a matter
of time before they got dragged into
this, since life insurers have been the
biggest reachers for yield out of
anyone. And they've already been quietly
pulling back. Well, it's starting to get
loud. According to the Financial Times
this past week, the bond market, the
freaking bond market, is now getting
cold feet, not just about private
credit, but also insurers exposure to
it. That's a big one, as was how the
Financial Times article elicited a,
let's call it, interesting response from
the American Council of Life Insurers.
In other words, now that the spotlight
is starting to expand to include not
just the private credit providers, the
shadow bankers, but also those who fund
them, the insurance companies,
and we're starting to hear from them and
how they must have come to the Blue Owl
School of Crisis Management. It is
really that bad. When they protest this
much, it's difficult to take them
seriously when they say there's nothing
to see here. Instead, what we're getting
is, as I already just said, a double
dose of stage two, both hedge funds and
insurance companies. And as Mr. Turman
of Deutsche Bank said not long ago, if
it wasn't for the Iran conflict, this
would be on the front page everywhere.
As far as insurance goes, I said this in
a video earlier this week, up until now
it's been the dog which didn't bark. The
big bankers like Jamie Dimon and, you
know, Solomon over there at Goldman,
they can't stop talking about the
private credit bus because this time,
unlike last time, it's not their necks
that are in the noose. Instead, it's
Blue Owls.
But that was only the beginning. Follow
the money. In other words, where did
Blue Owl, Blackstone, Cliffwater, and
all the rest of these names that people
now heard of, where did they get their
funds? These shadow banks don't take in
deposits like regulated banks do. In
fact, that's why they're not considered
banks. They're called shadow banks
because they do relend money that they
do raise. And those shadow relenders
first get their funding from equity
investors and some other lenders.
They've got all the connections across
Wall Street to all the deepest pocketed
institutions, the big guys who have both
the cash and the need to do something
exciting with it. That's always going to
be the insurers, the pension funds, the
retirement planners, and the annuity
people. Shadow bank money mainly comes
from there, not necessarily JP Morgan.
And in that previous video, I showed you
where the insurers get their money. It
comes from policy holders. Sure, that's
a good place to start, but a lot of it
also comes from repo. There is more
leverage in this arrangement on the
insurance side than the insurance
companies have ever let on or ever will,
as we'll see.
I almost never do ads, and I say no to
the vast majority of those that are
brought to my attention, but I was
thrilled to be able to work with today's
video sponsor, Monetary Metals. And the
reason is because they're solving a big
problem, one that I've been highlighting
for a very long period of time. Gold is
a safe haven, but other than sitting in
a vault, it doesn't do anything.
Monetary Metals fixes that. They let you
earn real yield paid in physical gold
without giving up ownership. It's not a
fund, it's not a paper claim, it's your
gold working for you. Every month, more
gold gets deposited into your account.
It's simple, it's transparent, and it is
fully insured. If you believe in gold as
a long-term store of value as I do, this
changes everything. Go to
monetary-metals.com/snyder.
That's monetary-metals.com/snyder
for all the details. We absolutely thank
them for being the sponsor of today's
video, and now let's get back to it.
Okay, but that doesn't mean that JP
Morgan isn't important, especially at
the margins and especially under these
conditions. So, while insurance
companies and pension funds provide the
bulk of funding,
the banks do provide a lot of additional
funding and emergency funding. The
additional funding something called back
leverage, which I'll get to here. In
other words, shadow bank investment
vehicles, these hedge funds that you've
been hearing about, they raise their
money from the institutions and some
wealthy individuals, but to really
enhance their returns, they aren't just
re-lending to risky corporate borrowers
who are willing to pay them higher
interest coupons. The hedge funds also
pledge some of the assets that go into
their portfolios to banks like JP Morgan
to borrow a little bit additional from
them. This is leverage, or in this case
it's called back leverage because you're
not supposed to know about this. It's
how hedge funds performance can go from,
say, 8 or 9% to 12% or better. That's
the leverage. So, if you're seeing an
investment that's offering double-digit
returns, first off, basic rule of
finance, it's risky, no matter what Wall
Street and its salesmen tells you. And
second, it's got to have some leverage
in there somewhere. There's going to be
some in the fine print. There is no such
thing as free money huge returns. And in
addition to back leverage, banks like
JPMorgan offer the emergency credit
lines, which as you might imagine, the
hedge funds shadow bank are increasingly
desperate to access right now. As fund
investors pull their money, including as
we'll see insurance companies, the fund
managers just don't have the cash laying
around to pay for all those withdrawals.
So, they can either sell their assets,
which none of them want to do, or they
can arrange to borrow cash from a bank,
a regulated bank, to tide them over
until all of this blows over.
At least that's what they hope happens.
So, you can see how important bank
financing is at the margins, even if it
doesn't make up the bulk of shadow bank
funding. It's the marginal source of
leverage for returns, as well as that
emergency. So, if the banks begin to
pull back, that's stage two behavior,
back leverage gets more expensive or
even just disappears, which reduces the
returns available to these hedge funds,
which won't help them with their private
credit funds that are badly in need in
the performance just to keep their
investors from fleeing. Plus, if they
can't access the backstop that JPMorgan
and the other banks provide, since a
good chunk of their investors are
already pulling out, it's going to force
some of these funds to have to sell. And
that's when it gets to be full-blown
stage two.
Now, remember these stages cuz they're
important, and I went over them in my
last webinar a couple weeks ago. And
that's still available here on YouTube.
You can check it out on the channel.
Stage one, people start to realize it
was a bubble and there are a lot of
garbage, lots of errors being made,
money starts to reverse. However, banks
and other investors are still not quite
there yet. They stand behind whoever it
is that's in question, this case private
credit, and things generally equalize.
But, it's the first time that money
begins to flow out in reverse. But then,
you know, after the banks initially,
their impulse is to stand behind
everything, and other investors are
willing to keep putting money in. But
then, you get closer to stage two,
more investors begin pulling their money
out, and banks are increasingly
reluctant to provide the emergency
funding, let alone more back leverage.
And the chances and the incidences of
foreclosures goes way up. That's what
really defines stage two. And that
raises the probability of going all the
way into stage two towards stage three,
which is where you get into the systemic
part of the mess. We went over those
details, like I said, in the webinar.
So, what this video is really about is
documenting big couple of big stage two
signals. The one is what banks are
doing, and the other is what the
insurance companies and what's going on
with them. Now, for the banks, JPMorgan
started this last month. And because JPM
was doing it, you knew it wasn't going
to be long before everyone else
followed. And this is something else I
went over in the webinar, too, cuz it's
that important. Both what JPMorgan was
doing and what it would mean if, or
actually now, when the rest of the
banking sector inevitably did the same
thing. And what is that? Well, they're
distancing themselves via collateral.
Here's Bloomberg summing it up.
Some big banks are raising interest
rates for the leverage they provide, and
they're also marking down specific loans
posted as collateral. Behind the scenes,
that's prompting private credit fund
managers to swap out holdings from the
pools as banks, including JPMorgan
Chase, Goldman Sachs, and Barclays (I
love how they're actually naming names
here), exercise their right to write
down individual assets, according to
people involved in the talks who are
going to remain anonymous because
they're not authorized to speak, you
know the drill here. The strategies
banks are employing to address risks in
existing facilities aren't new, but
they're are more prevalent given the
turmoil rolling global markets, said the
people asking not to be blah blah blah.
Some banks, for example, are
scrutinizing loans made to software
companies and other industries at risk
of being disrupted by artificial
intelligence in the coming years,
basically doing due diligence that they
weren't doing beforehand. The stakes are
high enough that top bank executives are
getting directly involved in adjusting
the interest rates they charge for
leverage and tightening collateral
terms, some of the people said. Because
banks don't all have the same rates to
challenge assets, some may end up better
protected than rivals if private credit
defaults begin to rise. Now, this is
sort of misses the point. The stakes are
high for banks, sure.
Banks distancing themselves from private
credit like this isn't going to threaten
the banks themselves necessarily, but it
will leave the hedge fund shadow banks
without access to money they need to
avoid having to sell their assets. And
without the banks,
they'll sell assets and reduce their
prices even more than they may already
be doing. Plus, the more sales that
happen, the more the rest of the world
gets to see that distress, what's called
price discovery. And the lower the
prices go, the more fear it creates,
leading to more problems, more sales,
and so on as stage two entrenches and
heads toward stage three. And what will
make stage three more likely than
anything else? That's insurance
companies being forced to distance
themselves, too. Not just JP Morgan and
collateral swaps, we'd be talking about
the biggest source of money for private
credit and shadow bank hedge funds, the
biggest source by far. If the insurance
companies start to get cold feet, that's
game over. And that chill started a
little while ago. I went over this at
the end of February, how a couple of
insurance companies in Europe were
starting to talk about how, "Hey, we're
not so exposed to private credit and we
are separating ourselves, too." So,
here's a clip from that video at the end
of February.
So, AXA's position today is, "Okay,
there could be some fallout from this
growing mess, but not for us. Our
holdings are much less than all of our
peers." And while you can understand
what Mr. Bouberl is trying to do, I'm
not sure his admission actually achieves
the goal of reassuring anyone. He just
said, "Private credit is going to be
some degree of problem, so not nothing,
and all my competitors are really in
deep with it." Not that we didn't know
that, but for the most from the general
public, this is the first time they're
hearing it. So, great for AXA, not great
potentially for the entire system. And
once again, major European insurer now
saying, after reporting earnings, when
top management would love to talk about
anything else, Allianz's CFO admits
they're separating themselves from
trends in that part of the market. And
what does that mean? Exactly what you
think it does. Now we've got to the
point where, again, two of the biggest
financials in Europe are basically
saying they feel a little dirty about
having done what they did. To try to
clean it up, they're separating
themselves from the growing sense of,
I'm going to use the term, toxic waste.
That's the big one here.
So, combined with AXA pointing the
finger at Allianz and all the rest, it
represents a significant shift in
sentiment at the very least and likely
activity behind it. Everyone bought all
this stuff last year, couldn't get
enough of it. Now they're saying, "We're
distancing ourselves from it." It's
getting the reputation of toxic waste,
and that is potentially huge.
Yeah, toxic waste, that's the thing.
That's the real risk here, and that's
what brings us to what's going on this
week. So, yes, we got JP Morgan
collateral swaps revaluation, but
the more private credit gets to be
treated like toxic waste, what that
means is anyone who is anywhere near it
ends up becoming toxic, too. This is
what really turns subprime into
full-blown global monetary crisis. Not
saying that's what we're facing here.
It's the process, as I pointed out in
the webinar. Because at that point, the
entire financial system runs for the
hills, and then there's no stopping the
slide into stage three, whatever stage
three might end up looking like.
And if insurance companies that were
already getting nervous in late
February,
then what the Financial Times reported
just a couple days ago is not going to
help. What it said is that insurance
company debt has become of one of the
worst-performing sectors in the US
investment grade universe. Basically,
the freaking bond market is now looking
at insurance companies in a very funny
way, to the point that it's starting to
avoid insurers' debt. Not
catastrophically, not running for the
hills, but saying, "Hey, I need to take
a second look at what these people are
doing." Now, the Financial Times says
that in general, these bonds are now
yielding about a percentage point higher
than US Treasuries, which is a measure
of how much additional return the market
says it needs in order to buy and to
hold what are supposed to be safe life
insurance credit. And why? Obviously,
it's their exposure, their heavy
exposure to private credit. The bond
market isn't just, you know, saying
private credit's not nothing. It's
acting on those concerns and doing so in
an increasing fashion.
Not overwhelmingly avoiding insurance
companies, but enough at this stage to
signal the broader market is taking
toxic waste seriously.
And you know who took the Financial
Times article seriously? The life
insurance industry itself, or at least
one of the prominent trade groups that
represents it. They fired off a letter
immediately as soon as the article was
published and said, "What are you
talking about? There's nothing to see
here." Very blue owl ask.
This is the American Council of Life
Insurers, and their president who says
writes, quote, "The recent Financial
Times piece called Private Credit
Exposure turns investors away from US
life insurers April 14th, 2026 offers a
misleading representation of the
industry's private credit assets. If it
had included insights from life
insurers, the article would have
provided readers with important and
salient facts. Now,
honestly, we all know what anyone from
the life insurance business would say.
Same thing as Blue Owl and all the rest
of them thus far. Our investments are
strong, solid, universally loved and
adored. And our process is so
unimpeachable, it's as if God himself
did our underwriting. That's what they
would say. It's worthless. And then the
guy goes on to name-drop the IMF, S&P's
ratings as if that's a positive because
we all know how dependable ratings are
for questionable assets and keeping up
with the opaque exposures with all sorts
of boatloads of hidden leverage. So,
yeah, ratings agency, that's not a good
name to drop, either. He also tells us
insurance companies are, get this,
heavily regulated by the state, which is
even less reassuring, and that's even
before we get to something like
regulatory capture. Not to mention, I
went over this recently, how the
Treasury Department just just told those
same state regulators,
"Yeah, you may want to take a closer
look at private credit and the
tanglement with insurance companies." In
other words, it was indeed very Blue
Owl-esque, protesting a little too much
without actually saying anything
tangible or, more importantly, directly
addressing the serious questions that
are indeed swirling around everywhere.
Just more lashing out at against the
idea that, "Hey, the bond market, the
bond market, might be getting a little
uncomfortable about insurance reaching
for yield during the past couple of very
clear garbage years." So, yes, there are
two very big stage two matters going on
here. One, with the banks revaluing
collateral, and second, insurance
companies being drawn further and
further into this mess, which was, like
I said, inevitable. So, taking the
second one first, insurance companies,
what we're getting from them is more and
more whiffs or flavor, whatever scent
you want to call it, sense of toxic
waste.
I mean, retirement assets, they've been
the biggest source of money for private
credit and all the garbage, and there
is, as I went over, lots of leverage in
repo as well. Now, we aren't there yet,
but the idea of full toxic waste for
private credit is indeed getting closer,
and you can feel it. You can actually
see it. That's when it gets to be so bad
Now, it's not even about losses or too
many losses. It just becomes too many
questions that no one on the inside is
willing to honestly answer. Just more
bland corporate statements and
reassurances. But when the whole
financial world not only avoids private
credit assets, it also begins to pull
back from anyone who is adjacent to it,
that's when you know you've got a toxic
waste problem that is brewing. So, if
the entire bond market is darkening on
insurance company debt, that's a pretty
big sign. Not a huge one, not full
confirmation, but another one of those
milepost along the road, stage one,
stage two, heading towards stage three.
Because it will absolutely impact what
insurance companies do. They need to
preserve the debt market and the debt
market favor, or they're toast.
So, that could mean as as the toxic
waste label gets to be more accepted,
insurance companies, retirement assets,
the annuity provider, they're going to
have to cut many ties to private credit
just to save themselves the expense of
disfavoring the bond market. So, the
insurers really turn off the money to
the shadow banks, which by the way,
that's something that we've already
seen. I went over this before as well.
It was in the Blue Owl presentation.
When the company said it was only a
couple of investors that were
responsible for most of those huge
withdrawals. That was institutions. That
was the insurance companies. They're
already starting to turn off the money.
And now it's spilling over to the
outside world, to the bond market. And
then the second stage two thing,
what the banks are doing with
collateral, that's just as big. Like
insurers, starting with JP Morgan last
month, they've been distancing
themselves via collateral revaluation
and forcing these private credit shadow
banks to swap in other forms of
collateral. It's tightening down. It's a
credit cycle that continues to tighten.
Just making it more difficult for shadow
banks to avoid having to sell assets,
being forced to sell assets, going
further down the road of stage two,
closer to that point where you get
full-blown stage two asset sales in more
than just here or there.
Mr. Turman, the guy from Deutsche Bank,
was right. This stuff should be
everywhere. Well, that's okay. Well, the
stock market is in the midst of an
orgiastic frenzied euphoria over the
Iran conflict, the private credit
crisis, sadly, it's not going anywhere.
At least nowhere good. At every
opportunity over last six plus months,
it is only escalated and broadened,
spilled over, moved deeper into those
crisis stages, getting closer to toxic
waste status. And by the time everybody
might figure this out, the rest of the
financial world by then,
it would be already too late.
Now, it is important to understand how
insurance companies are neck deep in all
this and what that actually means,
including yes, repo and collateral
hidden leverage in the video link below.
As always, thank you very much for
joining me. Huge thank you, Euro Dollar
University members and subscribers. And
until next time,
take care.